[
  {
    "question": "What is the functional unit of the lungs?",
    "options": ["Bronchi", "Alveoli", "Bronchiole", "Larynx"],
    "answer": "Alveoli"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of the respiratory system is also known as the sound box?",
    "options": ["Trachea", "Pharynx", "Larynx", "Nostrils"],
    "answer": "Larynx"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of diaphragm during inhalation?",
    "options": [
      "It relaxes and decreases chest volume",
      "It contracts and increases chest volume",
      "It becomes convex",
      "It reduces oxygen level"
    ],
    "answer": "It contracts and increases chest volume"
  },
  {
    "question": "Human lungs contain how many alveoli approximately?",
    "options": ["750 million", "75 million", "500 million", "100 million"],
    "answer": "750 million"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which gas is transported by RBCs with the help of haemoglobin?",
    "options": ["Carbon dioxide", "Nitrogen", "Oxygen", "Methane"],
    "answer": "Oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which lung is slightly smaller and flat?",
    "options": ["Right Lung", "Both lungs are equal", "Left Lung", "None"],
    "answer": "Left Lung"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process is involved in the exchange of gases between alveoli and blood?",
    "options": ["Filtration", "Excretion", "Diffusion", "Conduction"],
    "answer": "Diffusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which respiratory disease is caused by inhalation of cane particles?",
    "options": ["Anthracosis", "Silicosis", "Bagassosis", "Asbestosis"],
    "answer": "Bagassosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following correctly defines 'Hypercapnia'?",
    "options": [
      "Deficiency of oxygen in cells",
      "Increase in rate of respiration",
      "Over saturation of carbon dioxide in the body",
      "Bluish discoloration of skin"
    ],
    "answer": "Over saturation of carbon dioxide in the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the colour of haemoglobin before it binds with oxygen?",
    "options": ["Red", "Green", "Purple", "Blue"],
    "answer": "Purple"
  },
  {
    "question": "What percentage of oxygen is present in inhaled air?",
    "options": ["78%", "21%", "0.04%", "44%"],
    "answer": "21%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which animal respires through tracheal respiration?",
    "options": ["Fish", "Frog", "Insect", "Amphibians"],
    "answer": "Insect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is an example of anaerobic respiration?",
    "options": [
      "Breathing through nose",
      "Fermentation of alcohol",
      "Oxygen transport by RBC",
      "Diffusion in alveoli"
    ],
    "answer": "Fermentation of alcohol"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bohrâ€™s Effect is related to:",
    "options": [
      "Increase in oxygen carrying capacity",
      "Increase in pH of blood",
      "Decrease in pH of blood",
      "Production of haemoglobin"
    ],
    "answer": "Decrease in pH of blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the full form of ATP released during respiration?",
    "options": [
      "Adenosine Triphosphate",
      "Amino Tris Phosphate",
      "Adenine Tris Phosphorus",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Adenosine Triphosphate"
  }
]
